Myron Beldock Papers MS212
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Myron Beldock Papers
1966 -- 1986
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Beldock, Myron
MS212
78.25 Linear Feet 66 boxes
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the Rubin Carter defense files. The bulk of the materials consist of legal files including copies of court transcripts, briefs, photographs, and witness statements; there is also a smaller body of correspondence, newspaper clippings, and handwritten notes. The "Defense File Drawers" contain materials dated from approximately 1966 to 1976, which largely have to do with Carter's 1976 trial. The "Cityside Archives" boxes date to approximately 1979 to 1986, and mainly relate to the defense's subsequent motions and appeals. This grouping also includes a manuscript of "Lazarus and The Hurricane" by Sam Chaiton and Terence Swinton. Notably, there are also ten audio cassettes from circa 1976 related to interviews and testimonies given at the trial.
Biographical / Historical
Myron Beldock (1929-2016) was a civil rights lawyer who specialized in wrongful convictions and judicial misconduct. He represented a number of high profile clients, including George Whitmore Jr., Rubin "Hurricane" Carter, John Artis, and the Central Park Five.
Myron Beldock was born on March 27, 1929 in Brooklyn, New York, to George and Irene Beldock. He graduated from Erasmus Hall High School (1946) and Hamilton College (1950) before serving in the United States Army from 1951-1954. He went on to graduate from Harvard Law School in 1958. Beldock served several years as the Assistant U.S. Attorney in the Eastern District of New York, before becoming an associate at a small firm and a single practitioner. In 1964, he started the law firm Beldock Levine & Hoffman with friends and fellow former Assistant U.S. Attorneys Elliot Hoffman and Larry Levine.
During his tenure at Beldock Levine & Hoffman, Beldock litigated a number of high profile criminal defense and civil rights cases, specializing in wrongful convictions and judicial misconduct. In 1965, he won the dismissal of an attempted rape charge against George Whitmore Jr., a black teenager who was also falsely accused of the Manhattan Career Girl Murders in 1963. The charges were dropped after Beldock challenged the accuser's identification of Whitmore, when it was revealed he was the only black man in the police lineup. It also became apparent that Whitmore was beaten by police into signing his confession after several days of interrogation. This fact would later be central to the 1966 Supreme Court Miranda decision, in which police officers are required to inform suspects of their right to remain silent and their right to legal representation.
Beldock also famously represented boxer Rubin "Hurricane" Carter and John Artis after they had been wrongfully accused of a triple homicide in New Jersey, which again was attributed to misidentification of the suspects and racial bias. The case became the subject of a song by Bob Dylan, a number of best-selling books, and the 1999 movie "The Hurricane."
Beldock also defended Yusef Salaam. Salaam was one of the Central Park Five, a group of men wrongly convicted for the beating and rape of a woman known as the Central Park Jogger in 1989. The men had been coerced into making false confessions, but were all convicted of various charges including rape, assault, robbery, riot, and attempted murder. Their convictions were overturned in 2002 after serial rapist Matias Reyes confessed to the crime.
Beldock married Elizabeth Pease in 1953, with whom he had four children. Beldock and Pease were divorced in 1969. Beldock was remarried in 1986 to Karen Dippold, a lawyer with his firm and later, his legal partner. They had one son. Beldock died on February 1, 2016 in Manhattan, New York.
Social justice; Civil rights lawyers; Judicial error -- United States; Carter, Rubin, 1937-2014
- Rubin Carter defense files, 1966 -- 1986; MS212.001; 78.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Legal files related to the defense of Rubin Carter by attorney Myron Beldock.
  Arrangement
  This series has not been processed. Materials were boxed one filing cabinet drawer at a time, following the Beldock firm's arrangement.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research. This series may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-1 702097 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.001 (Box 1)
    Open for research.
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-1 702097 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.002 (Box 2)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-2 702098 (1 of 3), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.003 (Box 3)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-2 702098 (2 of 3), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.004 (Box 4)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-2 702098 (3 of 3), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.005 (Box 5)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-3 702099, 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.006 (Box 6)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-4 702100 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.007 (Box 7)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-4 702100 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.008 (Box 8)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer A-5 702101, 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.009 (Box 9)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-1 702102 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.010 (Box 10)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-1 702102 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.011 (Box 11)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-2 702103 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.012 (Box 12)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-2 702103 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.013 (Box 13)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-3 702104 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.014 (Box 14)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-3 702104 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.015 (Box 15)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-4 702105 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.016 (Box 16)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-4 702105 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.017 (Box 17)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-5 702106 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.018 (Box 18)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-5 702106 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.019 (Box 19)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-1 702092 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.020 (Box 20)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-1 702092 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.021 (Box 21)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (10 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.022 (Box 22)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-2 702093 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.023 (Box 23)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-2 702093 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.024 (Box 24)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-3 702094 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.025 (Box 25)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-3 702094 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.026 (Box 26)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-4 702095 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.027 (Box 27)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-4 702095 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.028 (Box 28)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-5 702096 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.029 (Box 29)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer C-5 702096 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.030 (Box 30)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-1 702087 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.031 (Box 31)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-1 702087 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.032 (Box 32)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-2 702088 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.033 (Box 33)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer B-2 702103 (2 of 2) and Drawer D-2 702088 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.034 (Box 34)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-3 702089 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.035 (Box 35)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-3 702089 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.036 (Box 36)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-4 702090 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.037 (Box 37)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-4 702090 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.038 (Box 38)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-5 702091 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.039 (Box 39)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer D-5 702091 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.040 (Box 40)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-1 702082 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.041 (Box 41)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-1 702082 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.042 (Box 42)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-2 702083 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.043 (Box 43)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-2 702083 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.044 (Box 44)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-3 702084 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.045 (Box 45)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-3 702084 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.046 (Box 46)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-4 702085 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.047 (Box 47)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-4 702085 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.048 (Box 48)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-5 702086 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.049 (Box 49)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer E-5 702086 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.050 (Box 50)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer F-1 702077, 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.051 (Box 51)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer F-2 702078 (1 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.052 (Box 52)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer F-2 702078 (2 of 2), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.053 (Box 53)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer F-3 702079, 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.054 (Box 54)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer F-4 702080, 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.055 (Box 55)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer F-5 702081, 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.056 (Box 56)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (1 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.057 (Box 57)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (2 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.058 (Box 58)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (3 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.059 (Box 59)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (4 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.060 (Box 60)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (5 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.061 (Box 61)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (6 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.062 (Box 62)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (7 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.063 (Box 63)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (8 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.064 (Box 64)
  - Rubin Carter Defense Files Drawer Cityside Archives Box (9 of 10), 1966 -- 1985; MS212.001.065 (Box 65)
  - Audio cassettes related to Rubin Carter trial, 1976; MS212.001.066 (Box data_value_missing_f6e2dc15e2b90a6c0f557c4cc3049c82, Box 66)
    10 audio cassettes (interviews, testimonies, etc.) and one legal brief related to the Rubin Carter defense. Materials were discovered by Myron Beldock's firm during an office move months after the first transfer of his files.